

# Sergey Maslyakov, PhD

# R&D Leader, Architect, CTO Staff +1-214-717-4617 sam@mslk.org

# **Summary**

Software R&D Leader, Architect, and CTO Staff member brings the depth of 20+ years of industry experience across a broad spectrum of technologies from fault-tolerant web applications and cloud computing to microcontrollers and digital circuits.

Contributes to the success of organization by defining the future vision of the products for 1-5 years ahead aligned with business priorities and by driving the execution across various functions within the organization.

Evangelizes fundamental computing principles that are often overlooked behind numerous adaptation layers and frameworks.

Believes in the "working smart" strategy as key to delivering superior products on time, with quality, and within budget.

# **Expertise Areas**

Engineering Leadership	Full Software Product Lifecycle	R&D Process
Team Enablement, Productivity Multiplication, Cross-functional Collaboration, Technology Outlook, Executive Advisory	Requirements, Architecture, DevOps, Design, Implementation, Build and SCM, Continuous Integration, QA, Delivery, Service, Security, Sustaining	Agile, Waterfall, Release Planning, Export Control, Third- party License Evaluation, Open Source Contributions

### **Experience**

10/2015—Present Principal Architect at the CTO Office of Viavi Solutions (former JDSU)

Responsible for the road map, requirements, and architecture definition for the middleware

layer of a distributed telecom solution. Working with a team of exceptional Engineers on design and implementation. Security Prime at the CTO Office.

03/2015—10/2015 Principal DevOps Architect and Manager at Viavi Solutions (former JDSU)

Defined and implemented a DevOps function for a complex telecom product developed by a geographically distributed team. Orchestrated release delivery to customers and internal teams. Established build, packaging, and deployment processes. Provided support function to the field teams to significantly reduce the average problem resolution time. Contributed to the Product Architecture to devise future-proof and robust solutions. Managed a team of highly experienced and creative Engineers, who kept all these things moving forward.

- 01/2011—03/2015 Principal Engineer at Tektronix Communications, a Danaher Company
  Provided critical solutions to support and expand accounts exceeding \$100M annually. Devised innovative and robust solutions while maintaining focus on business requests and operational landscape. Managed expectations of external and internal customers. Mentored and lead teams around the globe.
- 08/2008—12/2010 Software Engineer IV at Tektronix Communications, a Danaher Company Delivered a number of innovative solutions on an extremely aggressive schedule to save \$30M annually. Dramatically improved product usability, performance, and robustness, which resulted in major gains in customer satisfaction level. Spearheaded a new customer-centric Fast Feature Development Team. Lead others by own example, openness, and efficient mentorship.
- 05/2000—07/2008 Software Engineer I, II, and III at Tektronix (former Inet Technologies)

  Completed a large number of complex projects within market-leading monitoring solution for wireless and land-line networks. Built and refined an advanced skill set in C++, UNIX, Linux, Solaris, SPARC, x86, Java, scripting, build systems, GNU toolchain, Motif, middleware, computer networking, distributed systems, high concurrency, real-time systems, performance optimization, advanced debugging techniques, Oracle, MySQL, SQLite, Cognos OLAP, telecommunications protocols, and many other areas.
- 06/1997—12/1997 **Technical Support Engineer at Nevsky Link ISP**Lead a 24/7 Customer Service and Technical Support Team.
- 09/1996—06/1997 **Programmer at Conversbank**Developed automation software for daily banking operations. Provided IT services to multiple geographically distributed branches of the bank.
- 01/1994—08/1996 **Software Engineer at North-West Center for Information Technologies**Supported deployment and maintained a large university campus LAN. Developed software for the internal needs of the organization.
- 01/1992—12/1993 Lead Programmer at OPTOK

Developed copyright protection software with hardware binding. Reverse-engineered and enhanced firmware for a custom Floppy Disk Controller for a PDP-11 computer.

#### **Education**

06/2005 **PhD in Electrical Engineering** from State Polytechnic University 12/1999 **MS in Electrical Engineering** from Texas Tech University

06/1997 MS in Computer Science from State Academy of Aerospace Instrumentation

# **Open Source Project Contributions**

LAME MP3 Encoder Apache ZooKeeper Monit